A Finding Aid to the Karl Gruppe papers, circa 1880-1985, in the Archives of American Art
Archives of American Art
Karl Gruppe papers
circa 1880-1985
Archives of American Art
Gruppe, Karl, b. 1893
AAA.grupkarl
Archival Resource Key
3 Linear feet
The papers of Karl Gruppe measure 3 linear feet and date from circa 1880-1985. They illustrate his career through biographical material, correspondence, project files, personal business records, and printed and photographic material.
Biographical / Historical
Karl Gruppe (1893-1982) was a sculptor who worked mainly in New York City.
Karl Heinrich Gruppe was born in Rochester, New York. He studied at the Royal Academy in Antwerp, Belgium with Franz Juris and with Karl Bitter at the Art Students League in New York. He was a sculptor in marble and bronze and held the position of Chief Sculptor of the Monument Restoration Project for the New York City Parks Department as part of the Public Works of Art Project.
In 1980 he was awarded the National Sculpture Society's "Special Medal of Honor". He was a member of the National Academy of Design (1968-1971) and served on the National Council of the National Academy of Design from 1956 to 1959, serving as Vice President in 1957. In 1950 he was elected academician. In 1960 Gruppe served as President of the National Sculpture Society and was appointed a member of the New York City Art Commission from 1944 to 1947. Away from the city he shared a studio with his brother Emile Gruppe in Rocky Neck, Massachusetts.
Karl Gruppe died in 1982 in Southold, New York.
Arrangement
This collection consists of six series.
Series 1: Biographical Material, circa 1932-1979 (.1 Linear feet: Box 1)
Series 2: Correspondence, circa 1914-1976 (.4 Linear feet: Box 1)
Series 3: Project Files, circa 1929-1965 (.6 Linear feet: Boxes 1-2)
Series 4: Personal Business Records, circa 1901-1969 (.9 Linear feet: Box 2)
Series 5: Printed Material, circa 1893-1978 (.4 Linear feet: Box 3)
Series 6: Photographic Material, circa 1880-1985 (.6 Linear feet: Box 3)
Scope and Contents
The Karl Gruppe papers measure 3 linear feet and date from circa 1880-1985.Biographical materials include a resume and family history of Gruppe and various biographical sketches of others. Correspondence is to and from Karl Gruppe and is with Karl Bitter and his family, the Society of Medalists, and David Oppenheim, and regards commissions and organizations. Project files consist of materials related to various projects completed by Gruppe including the Henry Hudson Memorial, the William Rufus King Memorial, and the Monument Restoration Project. Also included are projects for war memorials, a joint outdoor exhibition for the National Sculpture Society, and various Boroughs in New York City. Personal business records include those related to the National Academy of Design and National Sculpture Society including proceedings, financial material, business records, reports, and other materials. Also included are records relating to various other institutions and copyright records.
Printed material consists of exhibition announcements and catalogs, news clippings, materials related to Karl Bitter and Eisenhower College, and a published copy of The Dream City: A Portfolio of Photographic Views of the World's Columbian Exposition (1893). Also included are materials related to Gruppe's time working with the Public Works of Art Project in New York City. Photographic material includes personal photographs of Gruppe's family, and friends, including Laura Gardin (Fraser), Anthony de Francisci, Karl Bitter and the Bitter family, photographs of Marcella Sembrich, and photographs of the interior, garden, and studio of Karl Bitter. Also included are photographs of the Louisiana Purchase Exposition (1904) and photographs of Gruppe's artwork which include nitrate negatives stored separately.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research. Access to original papers requires an appointment and is limited to the Archives' Washington, D.C. Research Center.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Materials on reel N70-35 were lent for microfilming in 1970 by Karl Gruppe. The bulk of the microfilmed material and additional papers were donated in 1970-1973 by Karl Gruppe and by his daughter Elizabeth Gruppe Stover in 1986.
Separated Materials
The Archives of American Art also holds microfilm of material lent for microfilming (reel N70-35) including correspondence, clippings, and catalogs, 1920-1970, including items about the controversy over New York City's sculpture. Correspondents include Robert Moses, Edmond R. Amateis, Mary W. Harriman, Reginald Marsh, and Henry Wolf. Loaned materials were returned to the donor and are not described in the collection container inventory. Items were returned to Karl Gruppe after microfilming.
Existence and Location of Copies
Portions of the collection are available on 35mm microfilm reels 104 and N70-35 at the Archives of American Art offices and through interlibrary loan. Researchers should note that the arrangement of material described in the container inventory does not reflect the arrangement of the collection on microfilm.
Monuments -- New York (State) -- New York; Monuments -- Conservation and restoration; Sculpture -- Conservation and restoration -- New York (State) -- New York; Medals; Sculptors -- New York (State) -- New York -- Interviews; Medalists -- New York (State) -- New York; Film festivals; Public Works of Art Project
- Biographical Material, circa 1932-1979; Series 1; Archival Resource Key; .1 Linear feet Box 1
  Scope and Contents
  Biographical materials include a resume and family history of Gruppe and various biographical sketches of others.
  - Resume, circa 1979; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Family History, circa 1935; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Membership, Indoor Birdwatcher Society, circa 1932; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Biographical Sketches, Archival Resource Key
    - Brandt, Warren, circa 1961; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Cherry, Herman, circa 1961; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Morris, Kyle, circa 1960; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Zogbaum, Wilfrid, circa 1960; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Correspondence, circa 1914-1976; Series 2; Archival Resource Key; .4 Linear feet Box 1
  Correspondence is to and from Karl Gruppe and is with Karl Bitter and his family, the Society of Medalists, and David Oppenheim, and regards commissions and organizations.
  - Correspondence (1910s), circa 1915-1919; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence (1920s), circa 1922-1929; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence (1930s), circa 1930-1939; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence (1940s), circa 1940-1947; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence (1940s), circa 1948-1949; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence (1950s), circa 1950-1952; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence (1950s), circa 1953-1957; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence (1950s), circa 1958-1959; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence (1960s), circa 1960-1965; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence (1960s), circa 1966-1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence (1970s), circa 1976; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Alben W. Berkley Competition, circa 1949-1950; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Benjamin Franklin Ferguson Fund, circa 1949-1954; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - David Oppenheim, circa 1949-1951; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Ella Burr McManus Fund, circa 1949-1953; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Karl Bitter and Family, circa 1914-1966; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Medals and Memorials by Gruppe, circa 1919-1964; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Society of Medalists, circa 1949-1952; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Project Files, circa 1929-1965; Series 3; Archival Resource Key; .6 Linear feet Boxes 1-2
  Project files consist of materials related to various projects completed by Gruppe including the Henry Hudson Memorial, the William Rufus King Memorial, and the Monument Restoration Project. Also included are projects for war memorials, a joint outdoor exhibition for the National Sculpture Society, and various Boroughs in New York City. Material related to the New York City Boroughs consist of a list of monuments and fountains in New York City surveyed for renovation by Gruppe under the PWAP from 1934-1937. Each survey includes a general description, sometimes a photograph, a statement of its condition, repairs needed and renovation costs.
  - American Artists Professional League, circa 1955-1962; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - The American Federation of Arts, circa 1945-1950; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - The Architectural League, circa 1956; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - City of New York, Archival Resource Key
    - Borough of Bronx, circa 1934-1937; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Borough of Manhattan, circa 1935-1936; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Borough of Richmond, circa 1935-1936; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Fort Clinton, circa 1934-1947; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Henry Hudson Memorial, Archival Resource Key
    - Correspondence, circa 1937-1938; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - Blueprints, circa 1937-1959; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - Business Records and Printed Material, circa 1937-1959; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Medallic Art Company, circa 1950-1953; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Monument Restoration Project, circa 1934-1936; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 37-38)
  - National Sculpture Society, Joint Outdoor Exhibition, circa 1950; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - U.S. State Department, circa 1964-1965; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - William Rufus King Memorial, Archival Resource Key
    - Blueprints, circa 1930; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 41)
    - Correspondence, circa 1929-1930; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 42)
    - Notes, Sketches, and Business Records, circa 1930; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 43)
    - Photographs, circa 1930; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Designs for Sculptures, circa 1930-1950; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Plaster Casts for Museums, circa 1948; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - War Memorials, circa 1944-1948; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Miscellaneous Sculpture Competitions, circa 1949-1959; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Personal Business Records, circa 1901-1969; Series 4; Archival Resource Key; .9 Linear feet Box 2
  Personal business records include those related to the National Academy of Design and National Sculpture Society including proceedings, financial material, business records, reports, and other materials. Also included are records relating to various other institutions and copyright records.
  - Allied Artists of America, circa 1951-1963; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Art Commission Associates, circa 1949-1968; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - The Century Association, circa 1952; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - The Fine Arts Federation, circa 1938-1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - The First Art Film Festival in America, circa 1950-1957; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Municipal Art Society, circa 1949-1957; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Museum of Modern Art, New York, circa 1951-1952; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - National Academy of Design, Archival Resource Key
    - Business Records, circa 1951-1957; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Finance Committee, circa 1953-1954; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Proceedings, circa 1951-1952; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Proceedings, circa 1953-1955; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Proceedings, circa 1956-1957; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - National Sculpture Society, Archival Resource Key
    - Advisory Committee, circa 1949-1959; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Announcements of Meetings, circa 1949-1954; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Competition Program Committee, circa 1951-1952; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - President's Reports, circa 1950-1953; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Proceedings, circa 1947-1949; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Proceedings, circa 1950; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Proceedings, circa 1952-1953; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Proceedings, circa 1954; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Proceedings, circa 1955; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Proceedings, circa 1956; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Receipts and Disbursements, circa 1952-1953; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Miscellaneous, circa 1948-1953; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Report on Pan-American Exhibition, Buffalo, New York, circa 1901; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - The Studio Center of Art for Colleges, Budget, circa 1940; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Copyright Records, circa 1916-1937; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 31)
- Printed Material, circa 1893-1978; Series 5; Archival Resource Key; .4 Linear feet Box 3
  Printed material consists of exhibition announcements and catalogs, news clippings, materials related to Karl Bitter and Eisenhower College, and a published copy of The Dream City: A Portfolio of Photographic Views of the World's Columbian Exposition (1893). Also included are materials related to Gruppe's time working with the Public Works of Art Project in New York City.
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, circa 1940-1945; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - American Academy of Arts and Letters, circa 1953-1959; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - The Committee of Government and Art, circa 1953-1957; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - The Dream City: A Portfolio of Photographic Views of the World's Columbian Exposition (1893), circa 1893; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Eisenhower College, circa 1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Karl Bitter, circa 1914-1956; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Clippings, circa 1949-1978; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Invitations, circa 1945-1955; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Miscellaneous, circa 1949-1976; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Photographic Material, circa 1880-1985; Series 6; Archival Resource Key; .6 Linear feet Box 3
  Photographic material includes personal photographs of Gruppe's family, and friends, including Laura Gardin (Fraser), Anthony de Francisci, Karl Bitter and the Bitter family, photographs of Marcella Sembrich, and photographs of the interior, garden, and studio of Karl Bitter. Also included are photographs of the Louisiana Purchase Exposition (1904), and photographs of Gruppe's artwork which include nitrate negatives stored separately.
  - Personal Photographs, circa 1914-1918; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Marcella Sembrich, circa 1888; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Historical Artwork, circa 1890-1920; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Interior, Garden, and Studio of Karl Bitter, circa 1940; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Louisiana Purchase Exposition (1904) Photographs, circa 1904; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Photographs of Artwork, circa 1915-1985; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 15-20)
  - Nitrate Negatives, circa 1915-1985; Archival Resource Key (Box NTR2)
  - Nitrate Negatives, circa 1915-1985; Archival Resource Key (Box NTR5)
  - Photographs of Artwork by Others, Archival Resource Key
    - Cecil Howard and Ana Huntington, circa 1920; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - Chester Black, circa 1920; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - Daniel Chester French, circa 1915; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - Herbert Adams and Robert Aitken, circa 1911; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - Karl Bitter, circa 1880-1907; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 25-26)
    - Lachaise, Manship, and Gaudens, circa 1885-1926; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - Sterling Calder, circa 1915-1924; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - Unknown Artists, circa; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 29)